Welcome to the podcast.
>> Thank you.
>> You spent 2 years in jail. Nearly a
3-year sentence, wasn't it? Without
>> Yeah, it was 2 and 1/2 year sentence.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh for blowing the whistle on things CIA
were doing.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh and since then they've made your life
kind of difficult and life's changed a
lot.
>> to.
>> They've tried to.
For the people who might have may have
may have seen your face, may have seen
some clips, or maybe they don't even
know who you are.
>> Right.
>> How would you introduce yourself? Who
who were you before
all of that happened?
>> Sure. I'm John Kiriakou. I was a CIA
officer for
oh, about 14 and 1/2 years. And um
I rose up to be the chief of CIA
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
after the 9/11 attacks.
Um had actually some even more senior
jobs after that, but um
I objected to the CIA's torture program.
Uh at first internally and later on in
public to ABC News in 2007, December of
2007, I gave a nationally televised uh
interview to ABC News in which I said
that the CIA was torturing its
prisoners. Funny enough, the Bush
administration elected to not prosecute
me because
it is a crime
to classify a crime.
And they said that torture was a crime,
and so blowing the whistle on it was not
a crime, even if the the program had
been classified.
The Obama administration, under the
under the leadership of John Brennan,
however, uh asked the Justice Department
to secretly reopen the case against me.
They investigated me for 3 more years
and then finally charged me with five
felonies, including three counts of
espionage, for blowing the whistle on
the torture program.
>> In In that period, were you
were you working with them, or did you
quit and then
>> no, no. I I left in 2004.
>> Oh, okay. So, you were out before you
came public.
>> Yeah, I kept waiting for somebody to say
something about this illegal, clearly
illegal program.
And nobody did. And then finally I did.
And And then in the meantime I went into
the private sector for 4 years. I left
there and then I went to the I was the
chief investigator on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee for 2 and 1/2 years.
And then went into business for myself
and that's when
you know, they came down on me.
>> So, so you spent nearly 15 years
not just as some sort of by the sounds
of it some sort of lower level. You're
You're quite You're doing some some wild
[__]
>> Oh, yeah.
>> And from what I've seen and putting the
research together on you is you spent a
lot of time essentially
on the ground getting people to know
you, like you, and trust you enough
where they would give up secrets where
they're committing treason in their own
country.
>> Mhm.
>> Um I really want to focus a lot on the
topic of influence and and that whole
subject. And I'm curious to know based
off everything you know and what you've
done, what do you see most people get
wrong when it comes to trying to
influence someone to get something from
them?
>> You know, I'm always surprised at how
many people think that the CIA uses
coercion
>> Mhm.
>> to get people to give up secrets.
Coercion doesn't work. If I come up to
you and I say
you know, "Listen, give me your secrets
or I'm going to
you know, punch you in the face."
You're going to tell me to go fly a
kite.
>> Mhm.
>> But if I
befriend you and I
you know, spend money on you and we
vacation together and our wives become
friends and our kids become friends and
you know, we really become close.
You're going to do it just because we're
friends.
You know, if if we've been friends for a
year and we we took our families on a
ski trip together and we go out for guys
night and go have a couple of beers and
and we're really close.
And I say Morgan listen I
I could really use the
I'm having some trouble at work and
one thing that was really that would
really help me is I could really use the
plans to that new Russian tank
that you have access to. That would so
help me out. I would really be grateful.
You're going to do it because you like
me because we're friends not cuz I've
threatened you
or I have you know pictures of you with
a prostitute and I'm threatening to show
your wife. That that's not going to get
me anywhere.
>> But would you you would have all of
these things? Would you not have a plan
B, C, D?
>> don't even you don't even go down that
road. Nothing good is going to come of
that.
No. The Russians do it. The Israelis do
it.
We don't do it.
It's wasted time.
>> So cuz I'm I'm trying to put myself in
that position. I'm I'm picturing myself
with one of my best friends
known him forever decade. If I was
working if I had access to secret
intelligence I'm working with the
Australian government
and he said that to me I'd be like bro I
love you
>> But it's not going to happen.
>> No way. Yeah.
>> See and I would say the same thing
because you and I are not recruitable.
>> Right.
>> But
I haven't targeted you because you're a
great guy. I've targeted you because you
have access but you also have a gambling
problem or a drug problem or an alcohol
problem or maybe your wife's got cancer
and you would really really like for her
to be treated at the Mayo Clinic or
you're not making any money but you
really want your kid to go to a great
American University. I'm I'm looking for
a a hook a vulnerability. It's not just
cuz you're a great guy. I don't care if
you're a great guy. I'm going to pretend
that you're a great guy if you're not
but I'm also looking for that
vulnerability that I can latch on to.
>> So not everyone is recruitable.
>> No.
>> Does it sound
>> Most people, I would say, are not
recruitable.
>> What would you do if you're up against
someone who you've been found to
they're unrecruitable.
But, you needed it to get access to
something from them.
>> I'd break into their office and steal
it.
>> Okay.
Right. Okay.
Cuz I mean, there's so much I want to
un- unpack here. Um
from your recommendation, actually, I
saw you to say on another podcast,
you're like, um Homeland?
>> Yeah.
>> Did I can't remember what you said. Did
you say that was quite accurate?
>> Quite accurate. The only thing that's
not accurate about Homeland is if you go
nuts while you're overseas, they're
going to bring you home. They're not
going to just say, "Ah, it's kind of a
shame she went nuts. Well, let's leave
her in the field. Let her do do her
thing."
>> Little dramatic.
>> Yeah, it's it's too much.
>> Cuz I Yeah, I've been I've been watching
it and uh man, I'm like hooked. I'm
like, this is so fascinating, but I
think I'm fascinated because I'm like, I
could absolutely see how real this could
be.
>> Mhm.
>> Um like, but what I've seen is
um because I've been so fascinated on
the topic of influence just for such
long time and
um what I've seen from that show
is they'll get whatever they want
because
agencies like CIA have access to I mean
anything they can get. They can hack
into phones, they can spy on all this
stuff. So
>> Anything your heart desires.
>> So so when it comes down to getting you
to do something, what commonly comes up
is essentially blackmail.
They're like, "Whoa, we have pictures of
you going to this brothel. You sure you
don't want to give us this or we're
going to go to this and what"
So, this is that's for TV.
>> Mhm.
That's for TV.
>> Interesting. I feel like Santa's been um
I just found out Santa's not real.
>> Yeah. Sorry.
You know, when I first joined, one of my
instructors told told me that, you know,
back in the in the day, in the '50s, the
'60s, the '70s, yes, they used to try
that.
But, he told me that one time
one of his superiors, I guess, back in
the
back in the '70s, I suppose.
There was this cleric
and they set him up with a prostitute
and they took pictures through, you
know, a pinhole with a pinhole camera
of him, you know, humping the
prostitute. And then they went to him
and they said, "We want XYZ
information." And they laid out all
these pictures of him with the
prostitute. And he said, "Ooh, I'll take
that in an 8 by 10. And give me two of
those in 5 by 7. And how about some
wallet sizes for these?" It's like, "Get
the [__] out of here."
And they just made a policy decision
that this doesn't work.
>> Mhm.
>> These these just naked threats, no pun
intended, they they don't work.
And so
they just sort of revamped the way
approaches were made.
>> Mhm. How how would it not work? Cuz I I
would imagine
Well, I mean, every everyone's just got
their life, right?
>> it this way. Look at it this way.
You get caught with a prostitute. You
have two choices. You can confess to
your wife.
>> Mhm.
>> Maybe jeopardize your marriage, maybe
get a slap in the face.
Or you can commit treason and risk
execution. So, which one are you going
to pick?
>> Yeah, I guess that makes sense.
Yeah, so when everything's up against
I mean, that's the worst case is what
you're asking them to do.
>> Yeah.
>> Huh. Okay. So
so what you're sort of saying is it's
it's a complete other approach. It's
it's find someone from the get-go who
could possibly be recruitable, develop a
strong bond, strong communication,
strong sorry, strong relationship with
them. Get them to the point where they
like you enough where they just want to
do you a favor.
>> Mhm.
Look at it this way, too.
The CIA, any intelligence service, has
this thing called the asset acquisition
cycle.
It's spot, assess, develop, recruit.
So, I go to some diplomatic cocktail
party.
And and I spot you. And I say, "Hi, I'm
John. What's your name?" We exchange
business cards.
You work for the Canadian Embassy. Nice
to meet you. And I walk on to the next
guy. You work for the Russian Embassy or
the Chinese or the Cuban.
Okay, I'm going to maybe invite you to
lunch. So, I've spotted you. I've
assessed your access to information that
I might that I might want.
And then I begin the development phase.
This is the longest phase. It can go
months. It can go
years in some cases. But in that
development phase, I'm going to try to
assess if you have any vulnerabilities.
And I said it as I said a few minutes
ago, a vulnerability doesn't have to be
a bad thing. A vulnerability might mean
you just really really love your kids.
And you want the best for your kids. And
maybe the best means going to UCLA or
Harvard. Right? And your kid's not going
to get into Harvard.
I can get your kid into Harvard. And
I'll pay for it.
So, I'm developing you.
Do you like to drink? Do you cheat on
your wife? You know, maybe you and I
go out drinking or we go to Vegas for
the weekend or we figure something out.
Something that you really like to do.
And I can observe you over that period.
And look for that hook.
>> Mhm.
>> Now, 95 per In 95% of cases and studies
internal studies have been done about
this at the agency. 95% of the cases,
the hook is money.
Right? You want money. I have money.
I'll give the I'll give you the money if
you give me the information. It's just a
contractual arrangement. Very simple.
But the other 5% is kind of interesting.
Um in some cases, it's excitement. You
know, you've watched Homeland. You've
seen the James Bond movies. You want a
piece of that excitement, that
adrenaline rush of being clandestine.
You'd be surprised the people who are
just doing it for the rush.
>> Yeah.
>> And then the others are um
ideology.
You really, really love the United
States and you want to do it just to be
helpful to the United States or revenge.
You do it because you got passed over
for promotion and by God, you're going
to screw your boss
by volunteering to the Americans.
But 95% of the time, it's simply cash
for information.
>> Is this where you have a picture of them
on the board and you're mapping out
everything about them? Is this like
where where
where you're doing like analysis on
someone and trying to really figure out
like pro sorry, profiling somebody?
>> Yes.
>> So
>> It's exactly what
>> Can you walk us through there? So is I'm
imagining this would be Well, walk me
through actually profiling someone
because this is so fascinating.
>> So every year, the CIA and every
intelligence service begins the year
with something called an operating
directive.
What is it that we want to collect this
year?
What is it that's going to provide the
most help to the the formation, the
formulation of American foreign policy?
Okay, so we're interested in China,
Russia, North Korea, Iran, terrorism,
proliferation,
whatever.
And you rank these things, right?
There's tier zero which means, you know,
war is imminent.
Tier one is going to be China, Russia,
Iran.
Tier two might be I'm making this up. Uh
Cuba, who knows? Venezuela, whatever.
Down to tier five, which is
nobody cares about it. You know, EU
grain harvests. Nobody cares.
So, um
With this in mind, you know, as you go
out to this cocktail party, what the
operating directive is. You know what
you need to collect on. So, I go to a I
go to a cocktail party and I say hi to
you and you say hi to me and we shake
hands and I hand you my card. I'm John
Kiriakou from the American Embassy. You
say, "Oh, I work at the at the port."
I don't care about the port.
But I say, "Oh my gosh, that sounds so
interesting. What do you do at the port?
Oh, I always love ports. It's always so
exciting. Ships coming in, going out all
over the world. It's very
international." I'm just making all this
up to engage you.
And you say that there's a ship coming
in from wherever and it has a
shipment of this chemical.
I'm not a chemist. I don't know what
that means.
But when I go back to the embassy, I'm
going to say, "I met this guy. He
appears to be this age. He's this tall.
He's you know, this weight. He has brown
eyes. He has brown hair and he works at
the port. Here's his name. Here's his
title. Please let me know if you have
anything in the files, which they likely
will not." And I say he mentioned that
there's a ship coming in and has this
chemical on it.
And then they come back to me and they
say, "That's the precursor chemical for
cocaine."
So I say, "Aha, that I'm interested in."
So I call you and I say, "Hey, it was so
great meeting you the other day.
I would hope that you would allow me to
take you to dinner."
And nine times out of 10 you're going to
say yes. And we get together for dinner.
And I tell you
how much I enjoyed our conversation and
this thing at the port is so
fascinating. What do you like to do in
your spare time?
And you tell me something that you're
interested in.
I sort of gauge
where you would like to see this
relationship go.
Um maybe you mention, "Ah, I've been at
the port 10 years. I haven't been
promoted in 10 years." Okay, that's
important information for me.
Um so I look for ways that I can help
you.
Maybe you would love love love to go to
the United States on vacation. No
problem. I can have the visa ready in
the morning.
Um maybe like I said your wife is sick
or your child is sick or your child's
graduating from high school wants to go
to school in the states. Or you know
you've
your car broke down. I mean this
happened to me once. Like my car broke
down. I've had this car for 10 years. I
have literally no way to get to work.
I'm happy to buy you a car.
If you give me an hour in your code
room.
So you try to quickly assess
what it is this guy wants or needs and
what information he might have access to
that he'd be willing to give up.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay. So you look so
you're building rapport. That there's so
many avenues I want to get down. I like
to sort of go like linear through our
thing. So like let's say
um
so you're at a cocktail party. You're at
a networking event. You find somebody
you're talking.
How do you
cuz even for myself I'm one of those
extroverts introverts. I'm extrovert
when I want to be.
>> Yes.
>> And I can quickly my battery just I can
be at a thing I'll be like I'm bored.
Get me out. I can be in a I can
literally be in a conversation with
somebody
know that I should really talk to these
people but in my face just says like
[__] off.
>> Mhm.
>> How how do you first
especially for the introverts who are
watching this. How do you first get
yourself into a position where you can
be somewhat interested even though your
brain's kind of saying like I'm I just
don't want to I just don't want to talk
to these people. What's up legend? Real
quick. You're listening to this podcast
clearly because you're a big dreamer.
You're a big thinker and you want to
achieve massive freaking things on this
planet. What I know from my experience
and interviewing so many successful
people one of the fastest ways to
achieve what it is you want is to be in
the environment with those who are like
you and learning from people and where
you want want to. And that's why every
single year I run an event called Dream
Fest. This is our fifth year doing it.
We've had thousands and thousands of
guests in the past. We've had wicked
speakers. Last year we had Dan Martel
and this year we're even going bigger.
And every year we bring the best
speakers from the industry to help you
level up your skill set and your mindset
so you can create your dream life. It's
two full days live on the Gold Coast
here in Australia, but this year we're
even going to have a virtual option. So
head to the link in the description of
this episode and you're going to find
all the information you need. Get
yourself a ticket and I can't wait to
see you in August at Dream Fest.
>> Listen, listen, it's it's all an acting
job.
>> Okay.
>> It really is. First of all, you cannot
be a CIA operations officer and be an
introvert.
>> Oh, really?
>> The two are are incompatible with one
another. You have to genuinely love
doing this.
>> Okay.
>> I remember working for a guy, he was a
fantastic station chief. He was I mean,
he could have recruited me. I so enjoyed
just being around him. He was funny and
full of great stories and just a great
leader, a man of character. But he used
to say, "Listen, you going to this party
tonight?" "Yep, I'm going to the party."
He said, "I want you to show me 20
business cards tomorrow."
And I'd say, "Okay."
And so I would go from person to person
to person, make sure I got 20 business
cards or 25.
>> Mhm.
>> And then he would say,
"Not interested, not interested, not
interested. Ah, this guy, yeah, we'd be
interested in him."
And so I would,
you know, take the five or the 10 out of
the 20
that we might have operational interest
in and call and say, "Hey, I'd love to
take you to lunch. I had such a nice
time, you know, in our conversation the
other day."
>> Okay.
So, okay, so we you go back before you
would have your next encounter, are you
already starting to profile this person
from what you already know or is it just
is the is the intention itself the next
encounter to start deepening the
relationship and building more trust?
>> Oh,
yes and yes. So,
these these things are not mutually
exclusive. You've got to be
working on multiple people at any given
time, and you're going to be in
different phases of that relationship at
any given time. Maybe I just met you
last night at a cocktail party, but this
other guy I met
3 weeks ago, and we're already into the
relationship. And there's another guy I
met 6 months ago, and he and his wife
are having dinner with my wife and me,
you know, in some little out-of-the-way
place, so I can make him feel at ease.
So, you're going to be at different
phases
all at the same time, and trying to keep
five, six, eight people straight in your
mind.
And then it What you do to to make that
easier
is I wouldn't even wait for the next day
to write this up and send it to
headquarters. I would go right from the
dinner
through it through through a
surveillance detection route
back to the embassy, and I would write
it up that night. And it didn't matter
if I needed to be at the embassy until
1:00 in the morning. I was going to make
sure that this information got back
ASAP, so I didn't miss any of it.
>> Mhm. Okay. So, so walk me through this
this MICE framework then. So, cuz what
I've sort of got so far is number one,
be extroverted, sometimes even if you've
got to act it.
>> Yep.
>> Uh network with as many people. Find who
you're actually interested to pursue
another conversation.
Develop a relationship, but what you're
really looking for is where is a gap?
Where is a vulnerability they have? What
is something that they really need? Cuz
maybe they want it for pleasure, or
maybe they want it to avoid suffering.
Um so, for the listeners, walk us
through what does MICE stand for?
And how what MICE would use that?
>> is not a CIA acronym.
>> Okay.
>> That's just been kind of made up by the
public that's interested in this kind of
thing.
>> Interesting.
>> Um
Like I said, you can use Wow, so many
different
tools to recruit somebody with M money
being the most important one. Now, if
you've If you're a guy who's got, you
know, access to the local Communist
Party, that's moderately interesting to
me. It's
not terribly important. That might be
worth a couple thousand bucks a month.
If you're going to give me Osama bin
Laden's location,
that's going to be worth 25 million.
And I'm happy to give it to you in gold,
in diamonds,
in cash.
Uh we can set up a bank account for you.
We can give it to you in land, in any
country that you want to to go to. We
can work something out. But it's going
to be different for every single person.
It's going to be tailored.
Um
It's not
unheard of
for somebody to want the money, let's
say, in diamonds.
And so,
we've got a relationship with a guy who
has access to the diamonds.
I'm going to get, you know, 30 different
diamonds in all different sizes and
colors and clarity and shape. And I'm
going to give you the diamonds. And
then, if you need to cash in a diamond,
here's a phone number that you call.
And you ask for Mike. And the person's
going to say that Mike's not in right
now. May I take a message? And you say,
"Yeah, tell him that uh his Uncle Chuck
uh says hello and he hopes to see him at
Christmas." And that means meet me in 24
hours at the coffee shop at such and
such a,
you know, an intersection.
And
an officer will show up with an envelope
of cash.
You cash in one of your diamonds,
and then we just wait for the next
encounter.
>> Mhm.
So, I'm I'm trying to imagine So, I
guess everyone's different. Would it
would it be right by saying
cuz I'm shocked that money is the number
one.
>> Are you?
>> But, I'm also not because
>> Don't be.
>> As I was thinking cuz I I
>> People are greedy bastards.
>> Am I right by saying that because
probably the people CIA would be
recruiting
are probably not wealthy people.
>> Correct. They're mostly government
employees.
>> Yeah. So, they're all quite underpaid.
So, they would take cash.
>> Sure.
>> Yeah. So, what what about for someone
who
And I was actually also thinking this.
I'm like, am I motivated by my money? I
I think to some degree. And what I was
what I was thinking is
it would it would come down to how much
and in which time frame.
Cuz that's that's how like the mind
works. Because if somebody said,
I'll give you
a million dollars for doing this.
If I get a million dollars straight
away, that's exciting. But, if I got a
million dollars spread out over
a year or something like that, I'd be
like,
I mean, I could make that a you know
You know what I mean? So,
>> But, if you're a government employee
>> Yeah.
>> in some third world country
>> Money's everything.
>> making 10 or 12,000 dollars a year.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah. And I'm offering you 50,000
like right now.
50,000 is not a lot of money for the
CIA, but it's life-changing
for you if you're you know some Afghan
functionary in the government or you
know from whatever country,
it's life-changing.
>> Mhm.
>> You can pay off your entire family's
debts. You can buy a piece of land.
>> Yeah. So, what are the other ones then?
So, if you if you're trying to scope
somebody out and you're like, that
person money's not going to sway them.
What would be my other approach?
>> Well, like I said here early on in the
relationship, you're trying to determine
what the vulnerability is.
>> Mhm.
>> Oftentimes, at least in the course of my
career, it was medical care.
I had a guy volunteer once
because his wife had breast cancer.
>> Mhm.
>> And this was a we were living in a third
world country and
the medical care was substandard.
And this guy really loved his wife.
And he's like, "Can you help her?"
Like, yeah, of course I can.
We'll get her to the Mayo Clinic
and and she'll have the best cancer
treatment that's available anywhere.
And that's what we did.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
>> I've heard I've heard people talk about
So, you mentioned before, so ideology
>> Mhm.
>> um
coercion I think people talk about, but
you kind of ruled that one out. So,
you're saying it's completely cuz I was
thinking about I'm like
I I think the only time you'd ever
really use it is if you never wanted to
ever have that person ever like you ever
again.
>> Or look at it this way.
If somebody tried to use coercion
against me,
>> Mhm.
>> I might say, "Okay, meet me at 3:00 in
the morning at this intersection."
And then I'd blow his brains out.
Because if he's going to try to ruin my
life and put my life and my freedom in
jeopardy, he's going to die.
>> Mhm. So, talk to me about ideology then.
I mean, sorry, I ideology and the the
ego.
Like how are you I I I guess I'm trying
to just sort of dissect like if I'm I'm
going to sit down and read somebody I I
guess you you may have one approach cuz
you said before, "I don't have a plan B
or C." So, you're kind of going in
asking someone of something, but you
must be so certain that that is going to
work on them.
>> Well,
yes, but let me explain. So, there there
is such a thing called a cold pitch.
Cold pitches almost never ever work.
That is, I knock on your door, I say,
"I'm Bob from the CIA, and I know who
you are, and I need this information
from you."
That never works.
First of all, maybe I'm not Bob from the
CIA. Maybe I'm Igor from the KGB.
Or maybe I'm from your own
police force, and you're trying to
entrap me.
And so,
usually people run screaming from the
room. They call the cops. They call
their service. You get expelled. It's a
big
big kerfuffle.
So,
cold pitches don't work.
So, normally,
you work on a person for long enough
that you know they're going to say yes
to the pitch. And you know exactly what
it is that they're going to want from
you.
Right? You never go in unprepared. I I
had a I had a station chief once tell me
that in the in the 25-plus years he was
at the CIA, he never had a target say
no.
And I can tell you, in my 15 years, I
never had a target say no. Never.
Because if they say no, you're in a heap
of trouble. You're probably going to get
expelled from that country. Because if
they say no to you, they're probably
going to report you to their version of
the FBI,
and then it's going to be an
international incident.
So, you have to be 100% sure
that they're just as into this as you
are.
>> Mhm.
>> And this is going to be a mutually
beneficial relationship.
>> What are the fastest ways to
deepen rapport and trust with someone?
Cuz this is a thing that
there's some people I can connect with,
and like instantly hit it off.
And I think it just comes down to if we
are naturally a similar personality
type.
And then there's some people
I'm trying to connect with, and I'm
like, this is just so they're just such
a odd personality or they're nothing
like me and I can feel this is just like
I'm I can't go anywhere with this
person. And obviously with especially
podcasting, there's a bunch of guests
that I meet I'm like, I stay really good
friends with them. There's a few guests
I meet I'm like, ah just
I wouldn't talk to them outside the
episode. Um
is there a way around that internally?
>> Yeah.
>> Again, you are an actor.
>> Mhm.
>> You have to be an actor. And so even if
you're not connecting with somebody, by
God you better make it look like you're
connecting with them.
I I've told this story before where I
was instructed to target a foreign
diplomat.
And so
I did some light surveillance on him and
I learned that he would go to the same
coffee shop every day, 7 days a week.
9:00 in the morning he's at the coffee
shop. So one Saturday, I would went to
his coffee shop and I bumped into him
and I was like, oh my gosh, what a small
world. Hey, how are you? It's good to
see you again.
And um I asked him if I could sit with
him. So I sat with him and we sat and
had a conversation
and um drank our coffee.
And it became clear to me that he in
this conversation that he was gay.
And he was deeply closeted.
>> How did you discover that?
>> I just had a gut feeling.
And he he made a complaint in that
conversation that he had been passed
over for promotion.
And he made it sound
like even if he wasn't gay
his superiors believed he was gay.
And I thought, well they know him better
than I do. So if they think he's gay,
he's probably gay. So I reported back,
he's gay.
And
headquarters said, we want you to
pretend that you're gay.
And so I said, okay.
So
I call him back.
We end up going to dinner, then we go to
lunch, then we go to dinner again, and
then I got two tickets for a show, and
we went to the show, and went out for
sushi afterwards, and
and this went on for months.
And
he
he felt comfortable enough to complain
to me about the
the system in his foreign ministry, this
the promotion system in his foreign
ministry. I learned a lot.
And I was reporting everything back to
headquarters.
>> This was in Pakistan?
>> Oh, no, no. I I can't say where it was.
>> So, it wasn't in Pakistan, no.
So, um
it got to the point where,
I've told this story before, and people
have taken this to be a joke, and
they've made memes and clips, and I'm
speaking in a funny voice. It was It was
very serious.
He He invited me to dinner at his
apartment one night. So, I went to his
apartment, we had dinner, and then he
leaned in to kiss me.
And I wasn't
I was momentarily distracted, and so
instinctively, I backed off like this.
And he said, "Oh my god, I'm so sorry. I
thought you were gay." And I was like,
"Oh my god, I just screwed this up." And
I said,
"I am gay.
I'm just not into hairy guys."
And he's like, "Oh, I'm okay. Okay." And
I said, "Oh, I'm so sorry. I've led you
on." He said, "No, no, I think you're
great. I'm glad we're friends." I'm
like, "Oh my god, I think you're great,
too.
But we're not going to be a a couple."
And it was cool, because he respected
me. And
in the end, he gave me everything that I
asked for,
because
he was upset that he kept getting passed
over for promotion.
>> Mhm. he did it out of a sense of
revenge.
But he trusted me enough
to give it to me.
>> Okay.
And so my whole understanding with
developing and building rapport, it's a
lot of, you know, mirroring and matching
and blah blah blah.
Does it get any deeper than that of like
developing How can I develop deeper
trust to the point where someone's like,
"I I just feel like I can tell you
anything. I feel like I've known you for
so long."
>> Oh my god, you you read psychology books
in your spare time.
And the guy mentions offhandedly that he
likes fishing, you go learn how to fish
like well.
Or he likes uh you know, cricket, you
learn the intricacies of cricket. You
have a favorite team.
You can speak authoritatively about
cricket and the history of cricket.
Or Broadway or soccer or
whatever he happens to be interested in
you immerse yourself
in this.
You know, a couple a couple bosses I've
had over the years have paid me some
real compliments. One of them said, I
was a brand new analyst. I'd been on the
job like 6 months. And I was actually
offended by this at first cuz I I
misunderstood it.
But my boss said, "You know, you would
be a really terrific case officer."
And I was like, "Why? I'm not a good
enough analyst? Are you insulting me?"
>> What's the difference between the two?
>> An analyst sits in a cubicle and thinks
the big thoughts and writes papers.
>> And that's what you were doing most of.
>> At at in the beginning of my career.
>> Okay.
>> Case officers recruiting spies to steal
secrets.
And so he said, "No, what I mean is
you're extroverted, you're a nice guy,
and people like to be around you." Which
had never even occurred to me.
But it planted a seed in my mind that
maybe I will try operations. Maybe I
would be good at operations. And it
turned out that I was good at
operations. And then later in my career
when I had proven myself as an effective
operations officer
I recruited a guy
who was so sensitive that I couldn't
meet him in the country that I recruited
him in. And so headquarters said
fly him back to Washington. You fly a
different way back to Washington.
And we'll meet him here.
So we met him in a hotel here in
Washington.
And I invited my boss and a senior
operations officer and the senior
analyst
to come to the hotel and just sit and I
mean technically it was a debriefing,
but what it really was was a
get-to-know-you kind of session. And so
he said the the source said uh you know
this is my first time in the United
States and and I hope I have a couple of
days built in because I'd like to go to
New York and I've never you know seen a
Broadway show. I'd love to see a
Broadway show. And I said, "Oh, listen.
Aida just opened on Broadway." I had
just read a review in the New York
Times. "Aida just opened on Broadway.
Elton John did the uh did all of the
music. He scored it and I forget who was
the the lead actress and
the New York Times raved about it." I
said, "I'll get us tickets. We'll go to
New York together."
And he said, "Tell me about this sport
you have here, this baseball. What is
this?" I said, "Oh, we just got a team
in Washington, the Washington Nationals.
We're not very good, but it's but it's
fun and we're going to play the Yankees
and the Yankees are a legendary team.
I'll get us tickets. We'll go after
dinner."
And there was something else that we
talked about in that meeting. And
afterwards my boss came to me
and he said, "I have never seen someone
speak so authoritatively
on such disparate issues
as you did today. And then you did a
substantive debriefing.
And I said, "You know what it is? I love
this job.
That's what it is.
I don't even feel like this is work.
I couldn't wait to get to the office in
the morning
just to see what I had missed while I
was sleeping.
>> Mhm.
>> And so you either have it or you don't
have it.
And if you don't have it, cut losses and
go find something that's going to make
you happy.
>> If you were to have to recruit me now
into doing something based off like you
barely even know me. Or actually I don't
know if you scoped me out or anything.
>> Mhm.
>> Um what vulnerabilities do you see in
me? What would be your angle?
>> I'm not seeing any yet. You did mention
that you um went skiing
uh recently. And so I would press you on
that just to see where you've gone
skiing, how talented you are at skiing.
I'm actually not very good, but you
know, if you're around, there are a lot
of places we could go skiing. Have you
ever been to Park City? Have you ever
been to, you know, Steamboat Springs?
There's a place in Vermont and uh
you know, even in western Pennsylvania,
they're getting a ton of snow.
I would explore that. You mentioned that
uh you were in Florida the other day. I
love Florida.
Uh spring training has begun. If you
don't know anything about baseball, it'd
be fun to fly to Tampa
uh and uh and check out some of the
some of the spring training teams.
I haven't detected a vulnerability, but
I don't know you well enough yet. But I
would certainly explore that in
subsequent conversations.
>> So vulnerability to me, the word is
>> Yeah.
>> kind of
the connotation kind of feels like a
weakness.
>> Yes. It's
>> But it can be both is kind of what
you're
>> Exactly. That's a mistake to think of it
just as a weakness. Think of it as an
opening.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh-huh.
>> Cuz yeah, like what you were saying is
um
as soon as you mention the skiing sort
of snowboarding, but like yeah, if you
were to be like
I mean, you like snowboarding? Oh my
god, we're we're going to Aspen and you
can come. I'd be like, "Get out. I'm
in."
>> And I'd call a couple of my colleagues
and I'd say, "Listen, I've got a guy I'm
going to want to develop. He's a
snowboarder. I don't snowboard. You guys
do.
I'm going to tell him we've got a we've
got a thing going. We're going for the
weekend. We happen to have this extra
ticket. It's crazy. What a coincidence."
>> Mhm.
>> And they'd be all in.
>> Okay, this is very interesting. And how
how could it relate back to cuz this is
where I'm I'm trying to extract
everything CIA related is super
fascinating. And I try to extract it how
can we use it practically in life.
>> Mhm.
>> CIA have access to unlimited amounts of
money and all of these things. Anything
you need like I'll go and get you to
Harvard, blah blah blah.
>> It's a key right there.
>> Uh
the normal person doesn't have access to
those things.
>> That's right.
>> So, how might someone else go about that
then?
>> Sure, that's a good question. So, I have
a friend who has never been in the CIA,
has never expressed any interest in the
CIA, but he has all the skills of a
successful CIA officer.
And where he has succeeded is as a
fixer.
So, he's in a senior corporate position
now, consulting position.
And
if you are a Hollywood studio
and you want to make a movie in
Cuba.
Yeah, you can't.
We have sanctions on Cuba.
>> Mhm.
>> But there's a village in Colombia that
looks just like Havana.
So, he's going to do
all the legwork and you're going to be
able to make your movie in Colombia and
make it look like Cuba or
uh
I'll give you a real-life example that
he brought me in on.
Sacha Baron Cohen
wanted to do
a movie called Bruno.
And
my friend was not a Middle East expert
and I am. So he brought me in. Can you
advise Sacha Baron Cohen on how to make
this movie Bruno? I said of course. So
we have an initial meeting and Sacha
says
I want to film this section of the
movie, this portion of the movie in the
Middle East. And I said great. I said
the Libyans are begging us, this was
under Gaddafi, the Libyans are begging
us to film movies there. They'll give
us, you know, tax-free, they'll pay all
the expenses. He said, don't want to do
it in Libya. He said, as a Jew, I'm I'm
just afraid of going to Libya, I'm
afraid I'll never make it out. I just
don't even want to consider Libya.
And I said okay, we could do it in
Morocco, but Morocco has very unique
architecture. So everybody's going to
know that it's Morocco. He wanted to
make it look like you know, Syria,
Jordan, Israel. But everybody's going to
They're going to look at these mud these
mud houses, they're going to say it's
Morocco. That's Moroccan architecture.
It's like no, can't do that. He said,
let's do it in Jordan. And I said, yeah,
but
we could do it in Jordan, but we're
going to have to bring the Jordanian
intelligence service in on it because
they're one of the best services in the
world and they'll be honest like white
on rice. He said, nope.
Can't break cover, can't break
character.
Don't want to tell the Jordanians.
>> was he's going in
>> When when he's in character, he lives
the character.
>> Right.
>> He's a comedic genius and I don't use
the word genius lightly. I I've only
worked with a handful of people in my
life that I would consider to be
geniuses. He's a genius.
So